<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Plea for succession in opposition to popular exclusion wherein it is evidenced, that an association, or any other such method, is a more immediate way to arbitrary power and a more certain road to popery than a standing up to the right of succession can in any reason be supposed to be : with some remarques on Coleman and his letters.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225594</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282256</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282256</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90770)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2234:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Plea for succession in opposition to popular exclusion wherein it is evidenced, that an association, or any other such method, is a more immediate way to arbitrary power and a more certain road to popery than a standing up to the right of succession can in any reason be supposed to be : with some remarques on Coleman and his letters.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Constitutional history --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150165:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR SUCCESSION, In Oppoſition to Popular Excluſion.</p>
            <p>Wherein it is Evidenced, That an ASSOCIATION, Or any other ſuch METHOD; Is a more immediate way to Arbitrary Power; And a more certain Road to POPERY: Than a ſtanding up to the RIGHT of SUCCESSION, Can in any Reaſon be ſuppoſed to be.</p>
            <p>With ſome Remarques on Coleman, and his Letters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Davis,</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150165:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150165:2"/>
            <head>A PLEA FOR SUCCESSION, In Oppoſition to <hi>Popular Excluſion,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THESE Papers are part of an Anſwer to a Pamphlet Entituled, <hi>No PROTESTANT PLOT,</hi> part 1. and were deſign'd to have accompanyed the reſt in their travels and fortune in the World: But being an entire Diſcourſe of it ſelf, and run to this length, and being founded on ſo ſmall a part of the Libel; I reſolv'd for theſe, and other Reaſons to ſend it abroad by it ſelf.</p>
            <p>That Libel pleads, <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>They,</hi> viz. the Proteſtants, <hi>know what they are to hope for from a Popiſh Succeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we will obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Pamphlet acknowledges his <hi>Royal Highneſs,</hi> whom all Men know he underſtands by <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> to be Really Heir, and Lawful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to the Crown: a Truth, that was formerly deny'd by ſome, but now ſtands confirm'd by Three <hi>Houſes of Commons</hi> in their Votes of Excluſion. It being therefore the ſenſe of the <hi>Commons of England,</hi> as well as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of this Pamphlet, it is expected we ſhall hear no more tidings of a <hi>Black Box</hi> with Fine Novels, and <hi>True Proteſtant</hi> Rarities in it.</p>
            <p>He calls him a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We anſwer, he ſhould firſt prove before he calls him ſo. For he never declar'd himſelf ſuch; and thoſe Topicks, from whence they would prove this charge, do admit of very eaſie, and reaſonable anſwers. We well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this was a brand, they ſet upon His Royal Father, who was the Glory of all Proteſtant Princes; and that in order to the diſpoyling Him of His Crown, and Kingdoms. This was ſet upon all Loyal Subjects, in order to the ſeizure of their Eſtates. This is a brand ſet again upon His preſent Majeſty, who is worthily ſtiled <hi>Defender of the Faith:</hi> and on every honeſt man, that is ready to defend his King and Country: in order to the burying them all in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ruine. This is juſt like the Man's giving his Dog an ill name; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he deſerv'd it, but that the People might riſe and ſtone him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (if the burnt Child may dread the fire) we may ſuſpect that the ſame charge may be faſtned on His Royal Highneſs, not ſo much from merit, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150165:3"/>deſign. But was it apparently ſo, I might believe, not becauſe they ſay, but becauſe I ſee it. Their Teſtimony will induce me, rather to reject, than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the thing to which it is given: For even the world doth now ſee, That neither Truth, nor Juſtice, is to be found amongſt them.</p>
            <p>If the Proverb be true, <hi>viz. like Maſter, like Man,</hi> we muſt conclude His Royal Highneſs a Proteſtant, becauſe His Chaplains, and Retinue are ſuch; nor doth he mingle with the Service of the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>But becauſe ſuppoſitions grant nothing, and that our ſubject ſo requires, we will humbly beg the favour to ſuppoſe, That His Royal Highneſs was once a Roman Catholick; yet if ſo, it is very inconſequent to call him a <hi>Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor,</hi> becauſe that both ſpeaks Him a Papiſt now, and alſo ſuppoſes he will be ſuch at the very inſtant of Succeſſion; which lies beyond the reach of our knowledge. For if of a Proteſtant, he ever became a Roman Catholick, he may return to what he was; one change ſpeaks the poſſibility of another: for what hath been, may be again.</p>
            <p>But however, having faſtned this imputation on him, he would affright us with what we muſt expect under Him. <hi>They know what they muſt expect from a Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now view Him in His Anceſtors, and the World hath not been Bleſs'd with milder Princes, than the <hi>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARTS:</hi> and Wolves are never born of Lambs. View Him in His Royal Perſon, and you ſee no ugly Characters of a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Prince. View Him in His Conduct; and He hath, like a cheering Sun, thaw'd the Northern World, and overcome a <hi>Scotiſh Nation;</hi> not with Arms, but with Love, and Wiſdom; where He is now become, next His Majeſty, the Pride, and Darling of the Age. He hath there trod the Steps of His Royal Brother, in giving Lives to them, that made His own the mark, they aym'd at. Therefore that thus Wretch ſhould ſet his ugly paw on ſo fair a Character, is a Sin too great for any Goodneſs, leſs than their own, to Pardon.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. ſaith, <hi>He hath a Memory tenacious of old Injuries, and — not inclinable to Forgive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From both which together it is Evident, that their fears are founded, not ſo much on the Princes Nature, as their own Deſert. They know they have above all meaſures abuſed, and injur'd Him; and therefore think He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them. There is no Judge like an Evil Conſcience, whoſe Sentence will not be bob'd off by an <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth then is, ſome particulars have ſin'd themſelves (as their own Guilt tells them) beyond a Pardon, and therefore can find no expedient, but an <hi>Excluſion.</hi> A fine contrivance! To imbroyl Three Kingdoms in a Bloody War, and deſtroy Thouſands of Innocent Perſons, and hazard the whole at laſt; for the carrying off a few particular Offenders; and thoſe ſuch too, whoſe timely change may yet attone their former Wickedneſs. Such Men perplex our Affairs, and poſſeſs the People with an Evil Spirit of Jealouſie, and Fear. Such Men make ſtrange Chimerical Bugbears, and Hobgoblins; and then lay 'em in the Paths of Obedience, to affright poor ſilly Mortals out of their Way, their Wits, their Honeſty, and Lives at once.</p>
            <p>And certainly did the People know; were they ſo happy as to ſee, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of a few cunning Heads, who would uſe their Lives, and Fortunes, to the ends of their own Impunity, Covetouſneſs, and Ambition: they would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſit Deaf to all thoſe Charms, whereby they would tempt them to their own ruine. Some Men have Plotting Heads, but they want your Hands, and Purſes, to carry on their Deſigns: For the gaining which, they Bely the Government, Perjure Cauſes, and Dreſs up all things in the moſt Tragical Garbs, that Wit, and Malice can invent; that as, on the one Hand, they draw People by the Golden Dreams of a <hi>Goſpel-Magiſtracy,</hi> and a <hi>Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry;</hi> ſo on the other, they may fill them with Horror and Deſpair, under
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150165:3"/>preſent Eſtabliſhments; and by both together run them into thoſe Calamities which they would perſuade will otherwiſe come upon them. This is a meer, <hi>Kid-napping</hi> the People, as the <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Man did the Boy, by Lyes, and Sugar Plums, into an utter Slavery. A pretty Invention to tempt Men into Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and a State of War, for their own ſafety; into Plunders, and Death, for the preſervation of their Perſons, and Eſtates. A Cauſe, that ſome <hi>Whig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Councel, who quote Laws, as the Devil did Scripture; to the ends of Sin, and Miſchief, may encourage; but no honeſt Man perſuade.</p>
            <p>But in caſe Men will by ſuch <hi>Sirens</hi> be tempted from the Ships to a foam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sea: from Vines, and Fig-trees, to Arms, and Fields of Blood: from the ſecurity of their Eſtates, to Free Quarter, and Plunders: and from the ſafety of their Wives and Daughters, to Rapes and Violence: they are the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their own Liberties, and deſerve to ſtand ſcored for Fools and mad Men to all Poſterity. For why ſhould I hazard my Perſon, Family, and Eſtate, to all the Calamities of War; for the humour, and intereſt of a few Men, who by my ſufferings would ſave themſelves: and raiſe their own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Command on my ruine? Or why ſhould I from a fond Fear, and fooliſh Dread of Lawful Governors, only becauſe Deſigning Men put fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Vizors on them; run my ſelf into <hi>Arbitrary Power, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies</hi> of fellow Subjects, which the Nation hath ſo lately groaned under. Which yet is the end of all their Intrigues, their Clubs, Sallaries, culling of Juries, Conventicles, and Libels: they all conſpire in the Deſign of <hi>Spiriting</hi> Men from their King, and Country; to become Drudges in their own Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: till the whole Land be made a <hi>Carolina,</hi> a <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and a <hi>Jamaica,</hi> where cruel Saints would have the Rule over us.</p>
            <p>Now the particulars, the Libel would have us to fear from this Succeſſor, are two, <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and <hi>Popery:</hi> as the next Lines plainly diſcover.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, I will here make it out to the Reaſons of Men, that in caſe His Royal Highneſs, were now a Roman Catholick, yet our keeping up to the <hi>Right of Succeſſion,</hi> is not by many odds ſo ready, and certain a Road to <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> both, as the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or any other ſuch Popular way is.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> the caſe is plain.</p>
               <p>For it is the confidence, and ordinary boaſt of theſe Men, that they do not fear this, while the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is low. This is plain in the Speech of the <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> and from numerous inſtances among that Party. And this very Libel ſaith, <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. That the King hath <hi>need of the Love of His People:</hi> by which it is there plain, he means their Purſes, as well as Hearts. Whence they are ſo far from fearing the King ſhould Preſs them; that even they are bold to Preſs the King: and will yield Him no Mony, unleſs He dearly Buy it, with His own Prerogatives. Men ſerve themſelves on the neceſſities of the Crown; and are <hi>Arbitrary</hi> in making their own Will a Law, while they would have more ſimple minds believe the King is doing ſo.</p>
               <p>Now what is thus able to hinder all, that is <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> in the preſent King, is as apt, and powerful in its own Nature, to hinder it in His Succeſſor. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon what Grounds, or Reaſons, they do not fear this Evil under His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſty; upon the ſame Grounds, or Reaſons, they need not fear it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Succeeding Prince. At preſent then we are free, and even theſe Men themſelves do boaſt, we need not fear the Yoak: and conſequently where they cry out of any <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> it muſt be from Deſign, and not from any real Fear.</p>
               <p>Whereas if we follow the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or any <hi>Popular way of Excluſion,</hi> we do <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> at the very firſt motion, ſtep into all, that is <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> For hereby we caſt our Religion, Lives, and Fortunes, into the Power of a few Men, whom Faction, Guilt, or Intereſt, ſhall perſuade to head the Party.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150165:4"/>Which done, they muſt neceſſarily run us into another Bloody War, to beat down preſent Eſtabliſhments, and to fix their own placits in their room. Which cannot be done, without great Expences, and ſevere Taxations, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the pretty Tricks of <hi>Publick Faith,</hi> and the wheedling poor Girls out of all their Plate, <hi>viz. Thimbles, and Bodkins.</hi> Which Payments muſt be rais'd, not according to Laws, which are againſt them, but at their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: and they, that this way take a part, may as well take the whole. Then as to Order and Government, none can ſay what they will be, becauſe it will ever depend on the Wills of them, that at any time ſhall be uppermoſt. Here then our Perſons, and Eſtates, lye all at the mercy of every Proud, and Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Committee, who will never want, while the Subject hath it. This then is the Height, and Perfection, of what is <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> which yet is the inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concomitant of <hi>Popular Proceedings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in caſe theſe Men after a long, and profuſe expence of Treaſure and Blood, ſhall gain their point, in ſubduing the Powers; they muſt neceſſarily keep up a ſtanding Army to ſupport the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> and likewiſe ſecure all Elections to themſelves, that they may bring in one Member, as another fails; and Purge out that again, if it doth not juſt jump with the reſt. By which means we doubly enſlave both our ſelves, and Poſterity at once; that is, both to the head <hi>Aſſociators,</hi> or <hi>Covenanteers,</hi> call them what you will; and alſo to the Army that upholds them. Which two Bodies for Peace, and Mutual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, muſt indulge each other, and divide amongſt themſelves the ſpoils of the People, and the Fat of the Land. And I am ſure the People will find fellow Subjects, if once they gain the Government, more Proud, Covetous, and Tyrannical, than any, upon whom the Government Devolves by Legal, and expected Deſcents. For it hath ever been obſerved, that ſuddain, and great Advances, make Men inſufferably Imperious, Proud, and Covetous. And when Crown, and Church Lands, are devoured by hungry Armies, and leading Commons; the neceſſary Charge of many <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and of a ſtanding Army, will much exceed the Expences of a Crown. Beſides all the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, that Men of the Bench, and the Sword will have, when they are their own Carvers: which muſt all come out of the Subjects Pockets. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or any <hi>Popular way of Excluſion,</hi> brings Men immediatly under not only <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> but withal, under the moſt certain, neceſſary, and unſupportable Oppreſſions too.</p>
               <p>But ſome may here Object, that they will avoid all this miſchief, for they will only put His Royal Highneſs by; and clap another in the Throne. They will alter a Perſon, but leave the Government untouch'd, till Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ways ſhall Purge, and Correct the Laws.</p>
               <p>We anſwer, This is a right Fools Paradice; and as Impracticable a thing, as the building Caſtles in the Air. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Rebellion, if proſperous, can never ſet Bounds to it ſelf, that thus far, and no farther will we go. Which we prove two ways.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From matter of Fact; for the <hi>Commons</hi> that took up Arms againſt the late King, pretended they would only <hi>remove Evil Counſellors, and bring the King to His Parliament.</hi> And truly, I believe the Body of thoſe Men did intend no more, but to make the King a ſlave to His Parliament, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But this Army ſoon fell into many wretched Sects, and had as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Intereſts as Parties: by which means, while they all Conſpired againſt what was an Obſtruction to the whole; they were yet in conteſt, who ſhould make his beſt advantage of it, when the point ſhould be gain'd. Which done, the ſtrongeſt Party carries away the Ball, and follows not what was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by others, but what was moſt advantageous to themſelves. And while theſe uſe the Sweat, and Blood of Fools, that firſt began the War, to their own ends; up ſtarts a new Player, who changes the Scene, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fools
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150165:4"/>them all. And upon every change things ſtill run to a farther exceſs; till at laſt thoſe, who began, and ſet Bounds to this Monſter, <hi>viz. Popular Tumult,</hi> were inſlaved with them, whom they firſt oppoſed. This is juſt like the Man in the Horn, the farther he creeps, the more he is ſtraitned, till at laſt he would fain get out, if he could. When Men in theſe ways fight, as ſome yet ſpeak, <hi>pro aris, &amp; focis,</hi> they uſually fight, till they have nothing, but ſmoak and aſhes left them. For while Members were excluded; Generals, and other Commanders chang'd; and Governors crept up, and again thruſt down one another; we gradually fell under a Monſter of Government, that had ſo many Heads, we could neither number, nor well underſtand, which they were: and things were driven beſide, and beyond, the firſt intention, to ſuch Tragical events, that will bluſh in Hiſtory to all Poſterities.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From Reaſon, which gives us to expect the like miſchiefs from a like ſucceſs of Arms. For here are the ſame Parties, the ſame Principles, the ſame Intereſts, the ſame wicked Policies, cunning Heads, Self ends, and (which is the complement of all) the ſame Devil working in the Sons of Diſobedience, that there was before: whence we muſt expect the ſame Conteſts, and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; for the ſame Cauſe will ſtill produce the ſame Effect.</p>
               <p>If there be any alteration among theſe People, it is for the worſe: for they are much more giddy-headed, raſh, and implacable, than they were before the beginning of the laſt Rebellion. And the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who are for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though not for ſuch; are generally ſunk into <hi>Independency</hi> which is for ſuch a Government, that it is indeed for none at all. For all our Conventicles are in their preſent ſtate <hi>Independent;</hi> every ſuch Body, like a flock of wild Geeſe, following none, but their own giddy motions. If any thing guides them, it is meer Oppoſition, which once ceaſing, they fall by the Ears among themſelves. Therefore having lived <hi>Libertines</hi> ſo many Years, they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver receive any Yoak: and conſequently confuſions muſt be greater, and things run to farther exceſſes, than before. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. In caſe of ſucceſs of Arms, theſe Men would never deſign, or yield to ſet up a King. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. While they are in the way of Conqueſt, they will, as faſt as may be, ſeize not only all Church Lands, and honeſt Mens Eſtates, but all the Revenues of the Crown too: which, as they are gain'd, muſt go not only to the neceſſary ſupport of theſe kind of <hi>Commons,</hi> or <hi>States,</hi> and payment of the Army; but muſt be given to ſome as rewards of their Services, and to others to ſecure them to the Party; and when theſe leading Men have once got them in their Clutches, they will never reſign them; but will be againſt a King, that they may ſtill enjoy His Revenues.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Soldiers are always for continuing in Arms; and for that Reaſon alone, will be againſt a King, and a ſettled Government; which rendering them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, will ſoon Disband them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If they yield to any Form of Government, it will be ſuch, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may partake in; and therefore ſuch, whereby they may farther ſecure their own <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Proceedings.</p>
               <p>Men are quite-miſtaken in their meaſures between Lawful Governors, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers:</hi> The former have nothing, whether Power, or Revenues, but what is their own; and from them is to deſcend to their Heirs: therefore as they fear none, ſo they bend their thoughts to the good of the Subject, as well as of themſelves: and many times prefer the Peoples, before their own particular advantages: as His Majeſty hath done in many inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> in making the Thirty Ships of War more large, and fit for Service, than the Tax given by the Parliament would do: in paſſing the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Bill; and in maintaining about Three Years War at <hi>Tangier,</hi> to the expence of near One Hundred Thouſand Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> and bringing things to an honorable, and advantageous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150165:5"/>commodation; and all at the very time: when, beſide the keeping a Fleet of Ships continually in the <hi>Streights,</hi> for preſerving our Trade; the <hi>Commons</hi> did ſucceſſively ſignifie, they would give no Mony, how preſſing ſoever the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of State might be. As Kings are <hi>Fathers of their Country</hi> in the Language of Nature; and <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> in that of Revelation, ſo they have a <hi>Paternal</hi> Care, and Love of their Subjects; Providence hath made them a <hi>Sun,</hi> and a <hi>Shield,</hi> whoſe Influences, and Protection, reach to all Parts of their Dominions. The Peoples folly, and madneſs, may look upon their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, as diſtinct from that of the Crown; but Kings eſteem them ſo entwiſted together, that they cannot be ſeparate.</p>
               <p>But <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> have at the moſt but their own Lives in the caſe, the Devil knows who may follow 'em; therefore they care not how Beggarly they leave the Soil to the next Invader. They have nothing, but what is other Mens; whence they fear both the Right owner, and what is their only due, <hi>viz.</hi> Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and Execution for the Violences, they have done. Therefore all their Deſigns lie, not for the Peoples Good, but their own Preſervation. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing is ſo jealous as Guilt, they never think themſelves ſafe, but when their ſecurity, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sword, is in their own Hands: whence they will never part with their Power to any, for fear they ſhould, at leaſt accidentally, betray themſelves. The King before His Reſtauration, promiſed Pardon to all, the Regicides only excepted; the performance of which Promiſe, they might have been Infallibly certain of, both from the King's Nature, and the then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances of things: and yet both the Rump, and the Army, were as irreconcilably ſet againſt His Return, as if the One was to have been Roaſted, and the Other Tyed up, the firſt day the King ſhould ſet Foot on the Shore: and the Reaſon was not only that they might ſtill Domineer, and Eat up the People; but might ſtill ſtand their own Defenders. Nothing is ſo ſweet as ſtolen Honors, and Command: nor ſo ſatisfactory to a Guilty Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, as ſelf-Defence.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay the caſes are not alike: for the Army will ſet up a Perſon, from whom they will have no Pardons, but Smiles to receive for their Services. Thoſe looked upon the King at beſt, but as a reconciled Enemy; from whom they could hope for nothing, but to eſcape Hanging: but theſe will look upon this Perſon as their Friend, who will be ready to advance, and benefit them: and therefore will be more ready to ſet up him, than the others were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King.</p>
               <p>We Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this ſuppoſed Army will be as unwilling to be put out of a way to Live, and to give up the Power, and Revenues, they have got into their Hands, as the other were before; and conſequently will be as much againſt a King, as they.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Heirs to the Crown muſt be ſuppoſed, at leaſt ſome of 'em, ſtill in being; and therefore waiting an opportunity of recovering their own: for which very cauſe, as well as others, they will not part from their Power, in giving the Sword out of their Hands; leſt by ſome ſlip of Government, or any other means, the Right owner return; from whom (after a ſecond Rebellion) they muſt not expect ſo large an Indemnity.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies Rul'd the Empire, they were never willing to part from their Power; though indeed they made Emperors, yet they unmade them again at their pleaſure, and forc'd the Senate to confirm their next Election, that for many ſucceſſive Reigns, they ſtill rode Maſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. In like manner the Parliament Army would have ſhook off <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cromwell,</hi> though at laſt their General, and ſet up by themſelves: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could he have held it; had he lived but a little longer. Next they tumble down his Son <hi>Richard,</hi> and ſet up themſelves again under their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150165:5"/>
                  <hi>Lambert.</hi> Nor muſt you ever expect that another Army of the People, if it once come to tread down all Authority, and Laws, will act any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; becauſe it is their Intereſt to do ſo. They will not voluntarily give up their Arms, and become your Servants, and be turn'd a Begging at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; when they are once become your Maſters.</p>
               <p>But to return a little back, whom will you ſuppoſe this Army to ſet up? It muſt not be the Lawful Succeſſor, which is His Royal Highneſs, for whoſe Excluſion, they pretend to riſe: nor His next Heirs, who will not take it over a Fathers Head; and in whoſe Hands Rebels will not put themſelves, leaſt Juſtice ſhould overtake them. But it muſt be one, whom we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a very <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper;</hi> who therefore, like the <hi>Protector,</hi> muſt keep up this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſecure himſelf. For if he Disband them, he is expoſed to the Lawful Heir; to whom the Loyal Party will adhere, and great part of theſe Forces ſo Disbanded will fly; ſome out of revenge, and others, that they may ſtill have ſomthing to do. Therefore in fine it comes to this, <hi>viz.</hi> that you muſt Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ask this Army firſt, whether you ſhall have a King or not: and then afterwards, how long you ſhall keep Him. For if they ſtand, they are able to put by your King at pleaſure; and if Disbanded, they make way for the owner.</p>
               <p>People are thus vilely miſtaken, in reckoning what mighty feats, they may do by Arms; becauſe they do not conſider the different Intereſt of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of an Army. Take the People peaceably imbodyed together, and they are a Civil Society, whoſe Intereſt is Government, and Trade; without either of which they periſh: but raiſe an Army from amongſt this Body, let them ride over all Authority, and Power, and their circumſtances are quite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; for they are now unhous'd, disfurniſh'd of Goods, Tools, Implements, and Commodities: and ſome never had any: they are now grown Idle, Proud, and Imperious: and can neither Beg, nor Work. Therefore their Intereſt is quite altered too: which is no more to ſit under Laws, and follow their Labour, and Trades; but to continue in Arms, to inſlave, and eat up the People. And thoſe very Men of them, that have other thoughts now, yet will have theſe, if they ever fall into ſuch Circumſtances: a Man's mind, and ſentiments, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vary with his condition. For Men are always ready to follow their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts, to take their advantages, and make their own markets. Therefore the People in ſuch ways do but conjure up a Devil, which they will never be able to lay: and which will give them no King, unleſs ſuch an one, as <hi>Jupiter</hi> gave the <hi>Petitioning Frogs,</hi> which devoured ſome, and made all the reſt a weary of him.</p>
               <p>Nor is there any help in ſuch a caſe, unleſs it fall down from Heaven, as it did before; For the <hi>Commons,</hi> whom you ſuppoſe to have Commiſſioned theſe Forces, and from whom alone you can expect it; neither will, nor can help it. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They ſhare with the Army in their ſtollen Revenues, and Eſtates, <hi>ergo,</hi> will not help it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Army, if diſpleas'd, will exclude ſome Members, and terrifie the reſt; or ſet up a ſingle Perſon themſelves, who be ſure ſhall be one, that hath no pretences to the Crown, leſt he ſhould keep it longer, than he ſerves their Intereſt; but muſt be a Perſon whom themſelves may reign under: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the <hi>Commons</hi> cannot help it; but each muſt comply with the other for Mutual preſervation. The <hi>Commons</hi> muſt Vote Mony for the Army, and themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: and then the Army muſt force the People to pay it. Whence the Friends to this way will be utterly diſappointed, and find themſelves paſſed out of <hi>God's Bleſſing into the warm Sun;</hi> and will ſoon become a Thouſand times more weary of their Arms, than they are of what they pleaſe at preſent to call their <hi>Grievances.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150165:6"/>
               <p n="4">4. Look to the People, and there can be no expectation of a King from them, who are made up of ſo many, and ſo different Parties; of whom ſome can diſpenſe with the Name, but not with the Power of Kings; they would poſſibly give the Title, ſo they may keep the Authority themſelves: <hi>under whom</hi> (for he muſt not live above 'em) a King ſhould not be half ſo happy, as a Man, that hath but five honeſt Tenants, whereof one pays Ten, another Twelve, another Fifteen, and the other each about Twenty Pound <hi>per annum.</hi> For this Man knows what he hath to truſt to, and may command his own: but the other lives precariouſly, and can command nothing. Others are for an Univerſal equality: who, that themſelves might never want, would have none above 'em. Here are a pure ſort of Saints, that will indure none, but <hi>King Jeſus.</hi> And there a late Sect of <hi>Puritans,</hi> yet deſcended with the reſt from the old <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, demure things, a narrow Soul'd People, whoſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences cannot ſtretch ſo wide, as to call any Man <hi>Maſter,</hi> or own any <hi>Guide,</hi> but the <hi>Light within 'em.</hi> A ſpecial Medley! A Parcel like to pull down, and deſtroy, if they can; but not to Eſtabliſh, and Build up a Government. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord brought a <hi>Babel</hi> to nought, and ſhattered the firſt Monarchy in pieces, and hath ruin'd all the Empires of the World; <hi>Ergo</hi> the Poets, to ſignifie all her Works are Deſolation, Paint her in a tatter'd Garment; and if (after the Obſervation, and Experience of all Ages to the contrary) we expect to ſee her <hi>Erect</hi> a Throne, and <hi>Build up</hi> a Church, and that while ſhe is threatning the ruine of both; we betray our own weakneſs, and make our ſelves one of the greateſt Inſtances of Vanity, that the wiſe Man hath found under the Sun. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. They never can ſet up a King, if they would.</p>
               <p>For finding ſo much fault with the Power of Kings, they will never ſet up One, unleſs upon certain Terms, and Reſtrictions; making Him to hold His Crown, as one did of old, by <hi>feeding of an Horſe;</hi> or, it may be, ſome worſe Creatures, as <hi>Mules,</hi> and <hi>Aſſes.</hi> We may conclude the particulars ſome ſuch, as theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Imprimis,</hi> That the King ſhall keep none but <hi>True Proteſtant Miſſes,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> and other <hi>good People,</hi> uſe to do.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> That He ſhall keep no more Guards, than <hi>Oats,</hi> or <hi>Bedloe;</hi> upon pain of having them Indicted.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> That He ſhall Borrow no Mony, leſt He make His loving Subjects Enemies to the State.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> That He ſhall be <hi>Ruled</hi> by His good Subjects.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> —</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> —</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> — &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In which, the People will agree well enough. But the main difficulty will be about that, which they have the leaſt of, <hi>viz. Religion, and Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> It is this, they pretended to Fight for; therefore as every Party did ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his Blood, ſo every Party muſt be ſatisfied. This then is a Boat, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one muſt have his Oar in; till, like <hi>Noah</hi>'s <hi>Ark,</hi> it have in it Forty Beaſts for One Man. And if in this great concern, you put theſe Queſtions, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the People ſhall meet in a Steple-Houſe, a Barn, or Stable; or whether (leſt the Spirit ſhould be confin'd) they ſhall Aſſemble, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did, in the open Air? Whether they ſhall have ſet Preachers, or Gifted Men; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this, or either Sex; and whether theſe ſhall Propheſie by turns, or as the Spirit moves? When Baptiſm ſhall be Adminiſtered; and whether the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall be Baptized by Sprinkling, or Diping; and whether in a Wooden Diſh, a Platter, or a Kookingſtool? Whether they ſhall have Parochial, or Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches? Or whether the Preachers maintenance ſhall be rais'd by Tyth Pigs, or Womens Pettitoes? And you have cut them out Work for their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150165:6"/>whole lives. But take in all the great matters of Government, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Worſhip, and no two Parties can any more agree, than heat, and cold. For their Principles are monſtrouſly different, and the Parties ſo intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably ſtiff, they will yield in nothing: in all their Religious controverſies every Party are like thoſe, that told Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> they would not leave an <hi>hoof behind,</hi> but are reſolv'd to have every <hi>Beaſt of Opinion</hi> with 'em. And when the Church was fallen under them, they were ſet as much Tooth, and Nail, one againſt another. For the Biſhops were not more ſeverely dealt with, as to verbal Abuſes, by all Parties; than the <hi>Presbiterian</hi> afterward was by the <hi>Independent;</hi> and the <hi>Quaker</hi> by the reſt. Therefore though they now all Herd under the comprehenſive ſhade of <hi>True Proteſtants,</hi> yet if ever they run down preſent Eſtabliſhments, they fall into numerous little Fractions; which can no more accord, than <hi>Whig,</hi> and <hi>Tory:</hi> being as much <hi>Diſſenters</hi> one from another, as they are from the Church.</p>
               <p>If therefore any ſhall draw a Scheme of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity,</hi> it muſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accord either with no Party; but be in ſome points ſuited to more, or to all, and then it pleaſes none of 'em; or with only one, and then it diſpleaſes all the reſt. It is therefore impoſſible they ſhould ever agree upon what terms to ſet up a King; and conſequently impoſſible they ſhould ever ſet up any at all. But they muſt neceſſarily live in continual Feuds, and act as ſtrength, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhall enable 'em. Whence it muſt neceſſarily follow, that, either they muſt rend one another in pieces; or fall under ſome ſubtile head, that ſhall inſlave the whole. Therefore after all the tricks of wickedneſs againſt King, and Government; and hope of Chimerical conſtitutions; which, like your <hi>entia rationis,</hi> ſhall never be found any where elſe, but in Mens fanſies, theſe Men will at laſt (if they had their way) bring their Hogs to a <hi>fair Market;</hi> as the Devil before them, who choak'd 'em in the Lake.</p>
               <p>Therefore notwithſtanding this Objection of ſhutting out all theſe confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by ſetting up ſuch a Perſon; himſelf is like to fall from the greateſt Glories of the Kingdom, matters of the Crown only excepted; which Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries he once did, and may again, if himſelf pleaſe (and all good Men wiſh, and pray he would) injoy; to be toſſed up and down, as the Peoples ſlights: and the People themſelves to fall under that <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> which an <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> a <hi>Covenant,</hi> or a <hi>Popular Excluſion,</hi> unavoidably leads to. In which, if I may not be believed, yet I am ſure, that <hi>Caſſandra</hi> like, I ſpeak the Truth.</p>
               <p>The reſult then is this, that inſtead of Evils in <hi>poſſe,</hi> this is the way to have them in <hi>eſſe.</hi> And thus to inſlave our ſelves at preſent, leſt we ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved ſome time hereafter, we know not when; is to Act worſe than the Man, that Kill'd himſelf for fear of Death. For his Death was certain; but this ſuppoſed Slavery, Men fear, is not ſo. A deep piece indeed, whoſe Policies, we do not yet diſcern, to run into preſent, and intollerable Miſeries under fellow-Subjects; rather than live in a poſſibility of being miſerable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Lawful Governors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or any ſuch <hi>Popular</hi> way; is a more certain, or ready way to <hi>Popery,</hi> than a ſtanding up to the <hi>Right of Succeſſion,</hi> can in any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be ſuppoſed to be.</p>
               <p>For the Perſons, that muſt be ſuppoſed to <hi>Aſſociate,</hi> are of many very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and irreconcilable Opinions; therefore ſuch <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or <hi>Popular</hi> way of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> muſt be carried on, not only by a <hi>War,</hi> but by an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Tolleration</hi> too. For if any Party be debar'd its Liberty, it falls off from the reſt; and the <hi>Excluſion</hi> of one will ſignifie nothing; as reaching no ends at all, without the <hi>Excluding</hi> more; and the whole dividing will be ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150165:7"/>
               <p>And if ever they gain the Government, an Univerſal Liberty muſt ſtill continue: for no comprehenſion, nor any imaginable contrivance, can unite, and bring more than one Party to the ſame Rule; nor that one neither, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that Rule be of its own making: and conſequently Eſtabliſh any one way, what you will, and all the reſt fly off, and conſpire the breaking thoſe Methods. Nor can any one Party oblige all the reſt; becauſe the reſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction will ever be too ſtrong for one. And yet to Eſtabliſh a Tolleration by Univerſal conſent is impoſſible too; for the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> when uppermoſt, declared againſt this, as much as ever they did againſt <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take which part you will, <hi>a Tolleration,</hi> or <hi>no Tolleration;</hi> and all the Fat is in the fire, either on this hand or that. In fine then this muſt be ſuch a Liberty, which the People took, when there <hi>was no King in Iſrael; every one doing what ſeem'd good in his own eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which means every Party becomes a Body diſtinct of it ſelf, and we have as many Sciſms, and Separations, and Intereſts, as Parties: whence every one is againſt every one: and whilſt they are all endeavouring to promote every Man his Way, and Party above the reſt; they do hinder, and pull back one another, till they all fall together by the ears. Therefore ſuch <hi>Popular Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations,</hi> have War, Liberty, and Confuſion, their inſeparable adjuncts. Which things do give the greateſt advantage to <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which cauſe <hi>Oats</hi> tells you the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were ſtirring up the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt the Biſhops, and in defence of their Covenant: and the ſpring following they did riſe, and declare accordingly: and <hi>Fitz-Harys,</hi> who was an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, made a diſturbance the very deſign of that Libel, for which he ſuffered.</p>
               <p>Nor doth the ſame <hi>Oats</hi> ſay any leſs of a <hi>Tolleration;</hi> but ſpeaks it a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Intereſt. And <hi>Coleman</hi> in his long Letter, ſaith, that the next Seſſion of Parliament, They, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deſign'd the procuring a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> which, ſaith he, if we gain, will be <hi>half our point.</hi> In which laſt are many Authorities: for he was a Man, that underſtood the ſenſe of that Party, as much as any; and conſequently we have herein not his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sentiments only, but the Judgment of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who were ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged well ſeen in Politicks. And truly they had both <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> to ſupport this confidence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Reaſon pleads that an Univerſal <hi>Toleration</hi> muſt be much more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> than to <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are kept clear, and firm to their Principles, and lie in no danger of receiving any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of their Church: but <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> being kept to no Rule, run into all extravagancy, and receive any wild conceptions, that are ſuggeſted to them: therefore while <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are multiplying Opinions, changing, and oppoſing Parties; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are gathering Proſelytes from amongſt them all. Therefore if ſuch <hi>Toleration</hi> be advantageous to <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> which yet they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume; and therefore received it ſo joyfully, that <hi>Wild</hi> returns a Ballad of Thanks, and his Wiſe was ſo tranſported, ſhe leaves her Gridiron, and runs with an Herring tail hanging out at her mouth to hear the news; it muſt needs be much more advantageous to the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> and therefore conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſo.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe ſuch Liberty Exclude the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> yet it matters not much. For theſe creep into every Party, and under diſguiſes of Mechanicks, and gifted Men, will have Liberty of maintaining old, and inventing what new Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>Among which they promote eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such as ſet every Party againſt every one; and incline them, as much as may be, to the deſtroying one another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such, that diſpoſe Men for the receiving the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith: in which the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> hath went very far already: as in Doctrines of <hi>Reſiſtance, Infallibility,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150165:7"/>&amp;c. which former, <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have practiced beyond example: and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they as really attribute to their own Teachers, and Parties; as any <hi>Papiſts</hi> do to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Church. Now keep theſe Notions abſtractedly, and change but the Perſons, to whom they are attributed, that is, your Teachers for the <hi>Pope;</hi> your Parties for the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the work is none.</p>
               <p>Therefore under ſuch a Liberty, the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> either moves ſuch Parties to weaken one another, till himſelf becomes able to deal with them all: or elſe carries them on to a conceited <hi>Perfection,</hi> to ſit <hi>above Ordinances,</hi> to dream of <hi>Viſions,</hi> and <hi>Revelations,</hi> and a <hi>Light within 'em;</hi> which ſuperſede, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Scriptures. By which means every Man becomes a Guide, and a Rule to himſelf: and being beat off from all Religions, he is ready to receive that, which alone ſeems to promiſe him <hi>ſure footing,</hi> and a quiet repoſe; and to which certain Opinions already received do diſpoſe him. Then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſervation, and Experience ſhew, that <hi>de facto,</hi> it hath been ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: for the laſt <hi>Rebellion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> that did accompany each, brought us ſo near the Gates of <hi>Rome,</hi> that we cannot imagine what (in thoſe Circumſtances) could have ſtoped our courſe, but the expedient Mercy gave us, <hi>viz.</hi> His Majeſties Reſtauration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Popery</hi> never made ſuch advances from the firſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to the beginning of that <hi>Rebellion,</hi> as ſhe did from the <hi>Rebellion</hi> to the end of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation:</hi> nor had ſhe been near ſo conſiderable as now, was it not for the ſtrength, ſhe gain'd then.</p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or any <hi>Popular Excluſion,</hi> which neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduces a <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Toleration</hi> both; is the very Bait the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have been laying for us; the Game, they would fain have us at: and conſequently had theſe Men deſign'd to turn all to <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> at once; they could not poſſibly have cut out apter Methods that way, than an <hi>Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is. Whence the Nation muſt juſtly ſuſpect either the <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> or <hi>good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions</hi> of ſuch Men: however their Friends, who are Factors for another <hi>Rebellion,</hi> would perſuade us they are <hi>True Proteſtants,</hi> and the King's <hi>moſt Loyal Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas while we keep to the <hi>Right of Succeſſion,</hi> we enjoy our Peace, our Liberties, Laws, and Religion; which every Wiſe, and ſober Man, will hold, while he can: and not throw them away in a pet, becauſe ſome Politick Pates, that would fain be making their own Markets, would perſuade us to do ſo. And for the future there are ſo many hazards between His Royal Highneſs, and the Crown, from infectious Diſeaſes, which ſeize the ſtrong, and healthful; from decays of Nature, which the weak as well as age, are under; and from the many accidents, which the moſt careful, and reſerved, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to; eſpecially Perſons of generous, and braving Souls, as His Royal Highneſs is. Beſides Men's ignorance of his preſent ſentiments; and the changes, that time, Reaſonings, and Obſervation, may make upon the beſt, and moſt knowing Perſons: that it is very highly uncertain, whether he ever come to the Crown ſuch, as is here repreſented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>But ſuppoſe he ſhould, yet it is not in any Reaſon to be imagined, that it ſhould be poſſible for him to ſettle <hi>Popery</hi> amongſt us. Indeed when Men look upon the thing in the groſs, they huddle up a thouſand difficulties together, and make nothing of 'em: but when they come to conſider the particular means, and ways, relation being had to the State, and Circumſtances of things, whereby it muſt be done, if ever it be done; they will ſoon find their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence broken; and themſelves at a loſs in ſhewing it fairly probable. For if it be done at all, it muſt be either by Law, or Arms; but by neither of theſe; <hi>ergo</hi> not at all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not by Law; becauſe all our Laws are againſt <hi>Popery.</hi> Nor are any new ones like to be made in our times in favor of it. For in all our laſt Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150165:8"/>of Repreſentatives, let but a ſly Knave ſet the Brand of <hi>Papiſt</hi> on the moſt known, and Loyal Proteſtant; and the People fly him as a <hi>Baſilick,</hi> that is ſaid to kill with ſight, or breath; notwithſtanding we are bleſſed with a Prince, who ſo conſtantly declares both by His Words, and Conduct, for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Proteſtant Religion, <hi>as it is now Eſtabliſhed by Law;</hi> whence it is not to be imagined they will (in our time at leaſt) be any way induced to Elect a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> or one, that ſhall ſeem <hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected, if ever we fall under a Prince, that may be ſuſpected to look any whit that way.</p>
               <p>For though nothing is more ſhallow, and unconſtant, than the People; firſt in determining what is <hi>Popery,</hi> branding now this, and preſently that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Doctrine, and Practice for ſuch; while <hi>Popery</hi> in many inſtances goes unſuſpected, and gives the denomination of a True Proteſtant: and then in ſelecting Methods of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> which are now one, preſently another; and ſomtimes the very way to let it in; as throwing open, and pulling down the Church, which is the beſt Fence and Bulwark againſt it. Yet great is their conſtancy in oppoſing what they take to be <hi>Popery;</hi> and though they miſtake in ſome particulars, yet they will eaſily ſee, when it is coming in the full Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon 'em. And eſpecially at ſuch a critical time, they will be incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly nice, and curious in their Elections.</p>
               <p>Indeed People may, perhaps, run into another extream in Electing Perſons, who by an over-haſty zeal, precipitant Councels, and a fearful flying, as they think, the fartheſt from <hi>Popery,</hi> may give it real advantages: but what it gains this way is not from deſign, but by accident: not from direct Laws, but by Conſequence. And indeed this is the Road, in which ſhe hath travel'd, and gain'd ground upon us, even under thoſe Men, who, we doubt not, deſign'd her utter Extirpation. And how ſerviceable People may be to the ends of <hi>Popery</hi> in this way, we fear; but do not ſuſpect they will Elect ſuch, that ſhall introduce it by a Law.</p>
               <p>Nor can we in Reaſon be affrighted at the inſtance under Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the condition of things is quite different now from. what it was then. For in thoſe times the Reformation was weak, and in it's Infancy, theſe Paths were uncouth, and ſtrange, and few minds heartily reconcil'd to 'em; great part of the Nation lay diſaffected, and ſtood Non-conformiſts to Proteſtant Eſtabliſhments: and the reſt of the People (a few only excepted) having real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no Religion in them, were for this, or t'other, and therefore ready upon a change to return to the old way, in which they were born, and their Fathers before 'em. Hearty Proteſtants were very few; <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtill made the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. It was therefore, perhaps, more eaſie for her to reſtore the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than to continue the Reformation; and things ſeem'd rather to <hi>return,</hi> than to <hi>be brought</hi> to their former ſtate. But now the Proteſtant Religion hath flouriſh'd ſo long amongſt us, that it hath taken deep Root, and is grown into a Tree, whoſe top reaches Heaven, and whoſe Branches are extended to all the corners of the Land; in her Boughs the Fowls of the Air do build; and under her ſhade the Beaſts of the People reſt. Men have been ſo terrified with <hi>Popiſh</hi> Hags, and Furies; and night-mared with <hi>Monks, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that they think there is no Monſter in <hi>Africa,</hi> nor Evil in the World, like theſe. Your <hi>Adamites,</hi> who are ſhameleſs as <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> and <hi>Sweet-Singers,</hi> who cloſe their ſervices with promiſcuous mixtures; and the <hi>Muggletonian,</hi> whoſe Divine Diſcourſes are the deepeſt Blaſphemies, will unite againſt this. This Sect no ſooner hears mention of a <hi>Pope,</hi> but it falls a <hi>quaking</hi> for fear it ſhould looſe it's own Infallibility, and be forced to transfer it to another; whilſt that, drunk with <hi>Venner</hi>'s Wine, flies to his Sword, and Muſquet, leſt the Vicar coming ſhould keep out's maſter. The <hi>Atheiſt</hi> will Swear, not by his God, for he hath none, but by the Heavens; and the Ranter by him, that made him; they will have no <hi>Popery,</hi> leſt they ſhould be bound to ſome Religion.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150165:8"/>The late Divine, who turns from Coat to Gown, from Gown to Coat again; like amphibious Animal, or water Rat, that lives in this, or t'other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and now contrary to the <hi>Antipendium</hi> way, ſtands with <hi>Brazen head,</hi> and <hi>Silver Screw,</hi> faſt ſet into all Sects at once: will for ever turn tail on <hi>Rome,</hi> leſt he ſhould be injoyn'd too hard a Pennance. Thoſe, whoſe hungry Titles have eat up all their <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Honor;</hi> with the whole Tribe of <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> who matter no Religion, are however againſt this: and he, that would not give a Groat for continuance of the Goſpel, is yet ready to venture his life againſt <hi>Popery.</hi> So diſparate, and unlike, are our preſent things, to what Queen <hi>Mary</hi> found, that we muſt not think what was eaſie then, to be poſſible to a <hi>Papiſt</hi> Prince now; and conſequently thoſe expedients, that would not have been ſufficient in her days, might yet have been ſufficient in ours.</p>
               <p>It is not likely then, that <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould (in our days at leaſt) come in by Law: Nor yet</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Arms; for if ſo, it muſt be either by our Arms alone, or in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with Foreign aids. But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not by our own Arms alone: For moſt of the Nobility, and many conſiderable Gentry, are Intereſted in Abby-Lands, or Impropriations: which things alone will ingage them againſt it. Religion moves but ſlow againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt, and preſent Advantages. And whereas it may be pleaded, that ſuch ſhall be recompens'd out of the Eſtates of Proteſtants; let it be conſidered;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Men will not eaſily part from an Eſtate in certain, for one in hopes only: with all Men preſent poſſeſſion goes far.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many of theſe will be ſuſpitious that themſelves may be the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, out of the other part of whoſe Eſtates, ſome Sons of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be rewarded.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are ſo many, that have already, and will yet ſuffer, for the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Intereſt, before this day can be ſuppoſed to come, who muſt be firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; that they muſt needs think, there will be but little, if any thing left for them.</p>
               <p>Therefore this Objection can be allowed but little, or no ſtrength to the ends, for which it is made. Whence conſider that the Body of our Nobility, and Gentry, are Proteſtants: the <hi>Papiſts</hi> being but like a few exceptions from a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule: and ſome of that Body, that ſome may think poſſible to be ſway'd, are ſtrengthned, and ſeeured by Intereſt. How few then are there, that are like to appear promoters of this Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It doth appear upon all publick occaſions, that the People are ſo far prejudiced againſt this way, that they are truly Impoyſoned: and inſtead of promoting the <hi>Papal,</hi> are ready to promote another Intereſt, to the ruine of all preſent Eſtabliſhments. So far are they tranſported with a blind, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitant zeal againſt it; that they are ready to commit thoſe very Treaſons, Rebellions, Murthers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the keeping it out, which themſelves ſay others would have done, for the bringing of it in.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Loyal Church-man, who never made the Bible ſpeak Treaſon, nor Religion the Patroneſs of Murther: but draws his Principles from precepts, and examples of Scripture; and from all Primitive Practice, hath learn'd to love his King, and therefore he will not reſiſt him: and to Love his Religion, and for that Reaſon, he will not help to deſtroy it. He hath been taught in the ſame Acts to <hi>Fear God,</hi> and to <hi>Honor the King;</hi> by yielding Paſſive, where he cannot yield Active Obedience. Therefore if he ſhall ever fall under a King, that ſhall ſet up <hi>Popery;</hi> he neither helps forward the work, nor reſiſts the Powers; but commits himſelf to Him, who governs the Kingdoms upon Earth: which of old was called, <hi>the Faith, and the Patience of the Saints.</hi> Now when theſe ſtand Neuter, it is utterly impoſſible that the <hi>Papiſt</hi> Party ſhould ever do any thing by Arms, upon the numerous Body of <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150165:9"/>
               <p>Indeed if <hi>Diſſenters</hi> prepare, or begin a reſiſtance, or if at any time they take up Arms againſt the King, the caſe is quite altered: for then the King, and all Loyal Subjects, whom theſe Parties all brand for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> are equally indangered: and then we are bound to defend both our King, and our ſelves, againſt fellow Subjects, who have no Authority to diſturb us.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe we fall under ſo nice, and trying a caſe, that we conceive we cannot defend our King, but we muſt enable Him to inſlave our ſelves and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies together: yet however, we muſt do our Duty, and leave the event to God. For we are not to ſin our ſelves, that thereby we may prevent others from doing ſo. You cry <hi>Popery</hi> is coming, and therefore Rebel: now we do not ſee the <hi>Popery,</hi> but we ſee the Rebellion: we cannot tell whether that will ever come; but we ſee the other is come already. Now we are to take the ſafeſt ſide; but if we joyn with you, we may be gull'd into a needleſs War, as many were in the time of the late King; whereas by a Rebellion, the Powers, the Government, and every private Intereſt are indangered. Moreover, if we run on your ſide; we are ſure to be undone, which way ſoever the Victory falls: for if you are overcome, we periſh with you, as Malefactors; but if you do overcome, we are ruin'd by you: and if we ſit ſtill, you deſtroy us, and our King together. Therefore in ſuch a caſe, as duty commands, ſo ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty preſſes us, to defend our ſelves, and King at once; without conſidering Him as ſuch, but ſimply as our King, and therefore whether he be this, or that: which is agreeable to the voice of God, both in Nature, and Revelation too. And indeed if we allow any Liberty of reſiſtance, we bring confuſion, into the World; ſet all Government upon Hinges, and make a gap for all manner of Villanies to creep in at. Whence St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcours'd like a Polititian, as well as a Divine, when he commanded the <hi>Romans</hi> to ſubmit, and not to reſiſt the Powers, even when <hi>Nero</hi> was their Emperor, who was juſtly branded for the Monſter of Mankind. Therefore unleſs <hi>Diſſenters</hi> by their Rebellions give ſuch advantages to <hi>Popery;</hi> it cannot in our time come in by our own Arms. Nor,</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Foreign Aids. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If a King ſhall make uſe of ſuch, He takes the readieſt courſe imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſoblige His Proteſtant Subjects. Eſpecially ſince theſe Aids muſt be ſuppoſed to come from <hi>France:</hi> againſt whom the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have the greateſt antipathy of any People in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In caſe the <hi>French</hi> King come at all, he muſt come with very numerous Forces; and conſequently leave himſelf weak at home: and thereby would draw all Neighbor Princes upon him; not only for the recovery of what he hath lately taken from them; but alſo to hinder his farther growth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may ſet up himſelf an Univerſal Monarch over this part of the World. By which means he would ſoon be drawn off to ſave his own at home.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We cannot in Reaſon think the King of <hi>England</hi> will ever call in thoſe; who, if too weak, looſe Him His Crown; and, if ſtrong enough, will take it from Him. For hereby he would bring Himſelf into a certain ruine, either by His Subjects at home, or His Aids from abroad.</p>
               <p>Look into the World, and tell me where Proteſtant, or <hi>Papiſt</hi> Princes, either in this or in former Ages, uſe to ſell their Kingdoms into the hands of any, for the ſake of forcing their Subjects to a Religion, they could not otherwiſe oblige 'em to. Honor, and ſecular Intereſt, cauſe Princes of the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to War one upon another. At this very time the Emperor, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, and <hi>Italian</hi> Princes, though all <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, are either in a War, or upon their Guards, every one waiting but till another ſtrikes. Queen <hi>Mary</hi> while ſettling <hi>Popery</hi> at home, loſt the laſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conqueſts on the Continent of <hi>France.</hi> And can we think that the King of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150165:9"/>
                  <hi>England</hi> will tread counter to all the Kings upon Earth? That he alone had rather have no Subjects, than not have them in all points ſuch, as himſelf could wiſh? Judg by your ſelves, and you will believe there is no Man ſo mad, as rather to have no Eſtate, than not have a few incumbrances with it.</p>
               <p>Indeed when Subjects are contending for the Government, they uſually call in Foreign aſſiſtance: for when once it comes to this point, that they muſt have ſuch Aids, or fall, it is eaſie determining what to do. For by ſuch means they may reach their end; however they can but fall; and, they think, better fall under a Foreigner, who by their means may gain the whole; than under the Powers, they would have diſpoſſeſs'd: for the former may give 'em Life: the latter the Gallows. Thus our <hi>True Proteſtant Rebels</hi> called in the <hi>Scots.</hi> And a piece Entituled, <hi>The growth of Knavery,</hi> tells you by what Lord they deſired the <hi>French</hi> King to be ready, in caſe they ſhould Pray his Aids. And this at that very time too, when they were charging the late King with <hi>Foreign Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencies;</hi> it being ever their way to charge thoſe Evils on the Government, which they are Acting their own ſelves: as again in this caſe, becauſe they may not Act: <hi>Arbitrarily</hi> in chuſing Sheriffs, contrary to the Law, and uſage of this City for many Ages before us; and contrary to their own Order, in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, they cry out of <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> as if they could never make Perſons, and things appear ſo odious, as by putting them in their own Livery. Their Brethren the <hi>True Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> having Rebelled againſt their Emperor, call in the <hi>Turk,</hi> and are ſhuting out the Bible by the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> But as Kings may fall, but cannot riſe, ſo they are very jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their Intereſt both at home, and abroad, and induſtriouſly careful that they give none an advantage againſt them.</p>
               <p>And certainly none could have thought ſuch a thing of His Royal Highneſs, was it not for <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letter: which, as His Royal Highneſs did deny to be writ by His order, or knowledg, ſo we have all the Reaſon in the World to believe Him, not only from the unreaſonableneſs of the Hypotheſis, as before; but farther,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Intereſt, and Temper: who, if things ſucceded, was to have had a great place: and as he was a Man of zeal, and performances, ſo he had this vanity, that he loved to Magnifie each. Therefore that he might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear conſiderable, and drive on things as faſt as they could go; it is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly probable he might exceed in the accounts, he gave: eſpecially touching His Royal Highneſs, becauſe the thoughts of gaining, or honor of uſing His name in this matter, would both have Magnified <hi>Coleman</hi>'s fame, and merits, and alſo above any thing elſe, have put life into their affairs. It is uſual for aſpiring minds to derive a Reputation to themſelves, and their affairs, by pretending the favour of thoſe great Perſonages, who have but once Smiled, or paſſed a Courtſhip upon them. And eſpecially Men of deſigns advance their matters under the umbrage of thoſe Authorities, that they were never acquainted with. And in the caſe before us, the reproach, that might have been feared from the diſcovery of his prevarication, he might eaſily think to keep off, both by the commendation of his Zeal, and alſo by the preſent advantages, he expected to have made from ſuch an Account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From <hi>Oats,</hi> and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> who clear His Royal Highneſs from the PLOT: <hi>Oats</hi> in his Depoſitions Swears, That the <hi>Jeſuits durſt not truſt Him with the knowledge of it:</hi> giving this Reaſon, <hi>viz. for he would never agree to it.</hi> And again they reſolved, That if the Duke would not accept the Crown on their terms, they <hi>would ſend Him after the King.</hi> Now do you believe <hi>Oats,</hi> or no? If you do believe him, then acquit the Duke from the PLOT; if you do not, then you make him Perjured, and therefore to be believed in nothing: it comes then to this point, <hi>viz.</hi> that you muſt either believe the Duke was not acquainted with the PLOT, or elſe deſtroy all <hi>Oats</hi>'s Evidence.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150165:10"/>
               <p>Now obſerve the prodigious impudence of <hi>Dangerfield. Oats</hi> Swears the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> dare not truſt the Duke with knowledge of the PLOT: and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> that they dreaded He would never be reconciled to their Methods: yet this Monſter of Villains Swears, He was acquainted with the Deſign upon the King's Perſon. Now ſuppoſe ſuch a Deſign, and that His Royal Highneſs, were a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick; yet that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſhould firſt acquaint the Duke with that Deſign, and then ſuffer Him to Act in it Himſelf, and that with ſuch a Fellow as this, who hath always lived by wickedneſs; and whoſe Story, if true, exceeds that of <hi>Guzman,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Rogue,</hi> would juſtly render them as notorious in Folly, as ever they have been renown'd for Politicks. Was there nothing in it, but the Notoriety of the Perſon in forming, I could no more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Dangerfield</hi> in this, than I can commend the honeſty of <hi>Don Tomazo.</hi> In the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Trial, Mr. <hi>Treby, pag.</hi> 40. ſaith, they have proved the PLOT, by <hi>Evidence apparently invincible,</hi> — and by <hi>credible Perſons:</hi> amongſt whom was Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bernard Dennis.</hi> And Sir <hi>William Jones,</hi> another manager for the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> proves by Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> a Member of that <hi>Houſe,</hi> and divers others, that Mr. <hi>Turbervil,</hi> was a <hi>Man of the faireſt Reputation, pag.</hi> 153. But when the ſame Men are Evidences for the King at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> they are loaded with numerous Crimes, and thence made utterly incredible: but among 'em all, ſhew me ſuch a Fellow as this, and I ſhall hold him a Perſon worthy to be gaz'd at. Indeed the greater Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, the more likely to be imployed in ſuch a concern; but withal the more unlikely to be entruſted by ſuch a Perſonage; where a diſcovery would prove incomparably more diſadvantagious to his Perſon, and the whole Cauſe too, than if acted by an inferiour hand. That the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſhould be ſo ſhy of the Duke, as to the PLOT in general, and dread His diſlikes; and yet on a ſuddain ſhould be ſo bare-faced in this, the top, and perfection of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, charged upon them; is the moſt prodigious madneſs for any to ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>This Wretch was before Angling in another Water, but not catching the Fiſh, he comes to this: whence it is probable he was (according to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods) ſeeking where to make the beſt advantage; and if once they come to the factious, they are tyed in Golden Chains for ever ſtiring from 'em. And the rather may we conclude this, becauſe his charge is ſo ſuited to the humor, expectation, and deſire of thoſe Men; who, while they commended the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi> Evidences for ſo much as they had ſaid; withal let them know they were yet ſhort in not having charged the Queen, and the Duke of <hi>York.</hi> Theſe Diſcoveries, like paultry Infects, and ſome wretched Vermin half formed, and juſt peeping out of Corruption, crawling abroad <hi>in time;</hi> after ſome warm gleams had a while reſted upon 'em, we may eaſily gueſs their Cauſe, and Origen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> to tell the Duke of the other point, <hi>viz.</hi> the bringing in a Foreign Army, had been in effect to let him know, that they were felling thoſe Kingdoms into Foreign hands, which himſelf ſtands Heir to; which is in plain terms, that they were betraying his Intereſt, and deſtroying his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: a thing, that no Man in his private, and narrow capacity, would ever be brought to; for every one is for ſecuring his own: Therefore whatever ſome <hi>Jeſuits</hi> might intend; yet that they ſhould ever impart ſuch a thing to His Royal Highneſs, or that His Royal Highneſs ſhould Deſign, or Act in ſuch an Affair Himſelf, is the moſt fond, and unreaſonable fanſie in the World.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Coleman</hi> in accuſing the Duke as to what himſelf had writ, ſpoke what in that Confuſion might ſeem His Intereſt; regarding not truth, but his own ſafety: whereas <hi>Oats</hi> in his deliberate Depoſitions, and unconcern'd in this particular, whether ſo, or not; clears the Duke from having any knowledge of the PLOT at all, and conſequently of theſe Aids, which was one main part of it. Therefore if you believe <hi>Oats</hi> either an honeſt Man,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150165:10"/>or well acquainted with the intrigues of the <hi>Papiſt</hi> Party, and the particulars of the PLOT, without which he was not qualified for a Diſcovery, you muſt neceſſarily receive that part of his Depoſitions, which acquits His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from any knowledge of theſe matters. Therefore the Duke never know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor being ever likely to yield, to this ſuppoſal of Foreign Aids, <hi>Popery</hi> is not like to come in (at leaſt in our time) by Arms; and becauſe neither by Arms, nor by Law, therefore not at all.</p>
               <p>Unleſs you plead that if a <hi>Papiſt</hi> King (if any ſuch ſhall be) cannot ſettle it by Law, or Arms; yet he may do much by Favour, and Politick advances of it. It is true, by ſuch means it may make ſome advances, but cannot come to an Eſtabliſhment, or gain the Government: it is but an intruder, and will be ſoon thruſt out by the next Succeſſors, who after His Royal Highneſs, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by all Men to be Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>This Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> found very eaſie to do; and yet <hi>Popery</hi> was then of many Ages growth, and was but check'd, or interrupted, rather than removed. For though <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. diſſolved Abbies, yet it was <hi>Edward</hi> VI. that ſettled the Reformation, which was not half received, nor well underſtood by the Body of the People, before he dies. After whom Queen <hi>Mary</hi> reſtores, and continues <hi>Popery</hi> near Five Years longer. Whereas now it is a ſtranger, and generally diſliked; and in the Methods this ſuppoſition puts, it can make but very ſlow advances; nor can His Royal Highneſs be ſuppoſed (if He outlive the King at all) to have any conſiderable time to ſmile upon it. Therefore being not Eſtabliſhed by Law, nor ſecured by the Sword, it lives only as a <hi>Favourite,</hi> which at the departure of a King, goes off, and makes way, for the Darling of the next Succeſſor.</p>
               <p>If the Church of <hi>England</hi> though Eſtabliſh'd by Law, ſo hardly rubs through the crouds of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> who, every ſtep ſhe takes, grin, and ſhew their Teeth, and ſtretch out their threatning Paws; and deal by her as the Watchmen by the Spouſe; or the <hi>Sober Party</hi> by the Lord Mayor, at the late Election of <hi>Sh</hi>— juſtle, and buffer, and pull, or beat off her Veil from her; can we think that <hi>Popery</hi> can obtain, meerly becauſe ſuppoſed to be ſome little time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſufferance amongſt us?</p>
               <p>The reſult then is this, <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> or <hi>Popular</hi> way of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> puts us immediately under <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and the ready Road to <hi>Rome;</hi> while Succeſſion being circumſtantiated as it is, may very probably be no way capable of effecting the Evils, which Men would perſuade us to fear. Therefore while our Libel faith, <hi>we know what we muſt expect from a Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> we may more juſtly ſay, <hi>we know what we muſt expect from the True Proteſtant Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>In fine, it is certainly a moſt fond trouble, that we diſquiet our ſelves withal, about the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Queen may Dye, the King Marry, and leave Heirs of his own body. Or the Duke may Dye firſt, and the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> fall upon a Proteſtant. Indeed the King is the elder, but it is ſo little that it is recompenced in his advantages of being the firſt born: for it is held that the Seminal vertue is greater in the firſt, than in the ſecond Generation; and in this, than in the third, and ſo downwards; whence it is obſerved that the Eldeſt Brother generally outlives the Younger; unleſs in caſe of accidents, of contagious Diſeaſes, which ſeize the ſounder, and ſtronger Conſtitutions, rather than the weak, and the more diſpoſed to Corruption: and of ill Habits, or Diſeaſes, contracted by any kind of intemperance: accordingly we ſee His Majeſty is the ſtronger, and more likely to live; therefore it is not yet come to an even Caſt, the odds lie on the King's ſide. Therefore for this Reaſon only, the Evils under a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> are improbable, becauſe it is more probable they will not reach us, than that they will. And certainly it is the greateſt folly in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150165:11"/>World to trouble our ſelves with improbable Evils. Were theſe Evils certain, but yet at a diſtance, ſolely becauſe they are at a diſtance, we ought not by the fear of them to imbitter our lives at preſent. An anticipation of miſeries is a double miſery; and the former, which conſiſts in the fear, is the worſt, becauſe wilful; the latter more ſupportable, becauſe unavoidable: that is our ſin, this our unhappineſs only. The one we bear as Men, the other as Fools. But that men ſhould make their lives uneaſie by a load of Plagues, which are both at a diſtance, which we may never live to ſee come, in caſe they ever come; and alſo unlikely ever to come at all; is the buſineſs of men, that want both wit, and ſomething to do.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>French</hi> King, we know not, whether: he may live to ſee an alteration here; and if his Son do, it is uncertain what Spirit he may prove of. That Kingdom is ſet round with Enemies, and may be diſabled to tranſport Armies into another Soyl. Or, however theſe things happen, he is a likely inſtrument of ſeting up <hi>Popery</hi> in theſe Kingdoms, who is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it down in his own.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole matter then, I cannot believe theſe Men fear what they talk of, it is not their Paſſion, but their Policy. Even this Pamphlet in the ſecond part pretends the ſame fears under His preſent Majeſty, and yet in this part <hi>pag.</hi> 4. ſaith, he hath too <hi>much goodneſs;</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 5. that he hath too <hi>little mony to do it:</hi> themſelves Expound their own Riddle, and give us to underſtand, that by <hi>pretended Fears</hi> they would beguile us <hi>into real Evils.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis hujus Argumenti.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
